Translator: Joseph Geni Reviewer: Camille Martínez
번역: KI young Jang 검토: Jihyeon J. Kim
I am a chef
저는 요리사이자 식량 정책가입니다.
but I come from a whole family of teachers.
그렇지만 교육자 집안에서 자랐습니다.
My sister is a special ed teacher in Chicago.
제 누나는 시카고에서 특수교사로 일하고
My father just retired after 25 years teaching fifth grade.
아버지는 25년간 초등 교사로 근무 하시다가 은퇴하셨습니다.
My aunt and uncle were professors.
숙모와 삼촌은 대학 교수입니다.
My cousins all teach.
사촌들도 모두 가르치는 일을 합니다.
Everybody in my family, basically, teaches except for me.
집안에서 저만 제외 하고 모두 가르치는 일을 하죠.
They taught me that the only way to get the right answers
가족들은 제게 "올바른 답"을 찾는 유일한 길은
is to ask the right questions.
"올바른 질문하기"라고 가르쳤습니다.
So what are the right questions
그렇다면 올바른 질문이란 무엇일까요?
when it comes to improving the educational outcomes for our children?
아이들에게 더 나은 교육적 결과를 가져다 주기 위해서 말입니다.
There's obviously many important questions,
중요한 질문이 많이 있을테지만
but I think the following is a good place to start:
이 질문으로 시작해보죠.
What do we think the connection is
아이들의 지적인 성장과
between a child's growing mind
신체적 성장 사이의
and their growing body?
어떤 연결고리가 있을까요?
What can we expect our kids to learn
식단에 영양가는 없고 설탕만 가득하다면
if their diets are full of sugar and empty of nutrients?
아이들이 무슨 힘으로 공부를 할까요?
What can they possibly learn
말그대로 배가 고픈데
if their bodies are literally going hungry?
공부를 제대로 할 수 있을까요?
And with all the resources that we are pouring into schools,
무조건 학교에 투자하는 것을 멈추고
we should stop and ask ourselves:
스스로 질문해봅시다.
Are we really setting our kids up for success?
정말로 아이들이 성공할 수 있는 환경을 만들어 주고 있는지요.
Now, a few years ago,
몇 년 전
I was a judge on a cooking competition called "Chopped."
"Chopped"라는 요리경연에서 심사를 맡은 적이 있어요.
Four chefs compete with mystery ingredients
요리사 4명이 재료가 무언지 모른채
to see who can cook the best dishes.
즉석에서 최고의 요리를 만들어 내는 프로예요.
Except for this episode -- it was a very special one.
특이한 에피소드가 있었어요.
Instead of four overzealous chefs trying to break into the limelight --
주목 받으려 애쓰는 다른 참가자와는 다르게
something that I would know nothing about --
음, 저는 주목받는게 뭔지 모르지만요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
these chefs were school chefs;
학교 급식실 요리사들이 있었어요.
you know, the women that you used to call "lunch ladies,"
보통 "급식 아주머니"라고 부르던 분들이요.
but the ones I insist we call "school chefs."
하지만 전 "학교 주방장"이라고 해야 한다고 생각해요.
Now, these women -- God bless these women --
천사같은 이 이모님들은
spend their day cooking for thousands of kids,
하루 종일 수천 명의 아이들을 위해 아침 점심을 만들어요.
breakfast and lunch, with only $2.68 per lunch,
점심은 겨우 3천원밖에 안하죠.
with only about a dollar of that actually going to the food.
이 중에 천원 정도만 식재료로 사용합니다.
In this episode,
어쨌든 이 에피소드에서
the main-course mystery ingredient was quinoa.
이외의 식재료는 퀴노아였어요.
Now, I know it's been a long time
여러분들은 학교급식을 먹어본게
since most of you have had a school lunch,
상당히 오래전이겠죠.
and we've made a lot of progress on nutrition,
영양 측면에선 상당한 발전을 했지만
but quinoa still is not a staple in most school cafeterias.
퀴노아는 여전히 학교 급식에선 조연일 뿐이죠.
(Laughter)
(웃움)
So this was a challenge.
그래서 이건 도전이었죠.
But the dish that I will never forget was cooked by a woman
하지만 쉐릴 바바라라는 이모님은
named Cheryl Barbara.
평생 잊지 못할 요리를 선보였습니다.
Cheryl was the nutrition director
쉐릴씨는 수석 영양사로
at High School in the Community in Connecticut.
코네티컷 주 커뮤니티의 고등학교에 근무하고 있었습니다.
She cooked this delicious pasta.
파스타를 정말 맛있게 만들었죠..
It was amazing.
놀라울 정도죠.
It was a pappardelle with Italian sausage,
이탈리아 소시지, 케일, 파마산 치즈를 넣은
kale, Parmesan cheese.
파파르델레였어요.
It was delicious, like, restaurant-quality good, except --
고급 식당 수준이었어요.
she basically just threw the quinoa, pretty much uncooked,
그런데 쉐릴씨는 퀴노아를
into the dish.
거의 생으로 넣었습니다.
It was a strange choice,
매우 특이한 선택이었죠.
and it was super crunchy.
기가막히게 딱딱했어요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
So I took on the TV accusatory judge thing that you're supposed to do,
참가자를 압박하는 역할을 했던 저는
and I asked her why she did that.
왜 이런 선택을 했는지 날카롭게 질문했죠.
Cheryl responded, "Well, first, I don't know what quinoa is."
쉐릴씨가 말하길 "글쎄요, 근데 저.. 퀴노아가 뭐죠?"
(Laughter)
(웃음)
"But I do know that it's a Monday,
전 퀴노아가 뭔진 모르지만 월요일이면
and that in my school, at High School in the Community,
학교 급식실로 출근해
I always cook pasta."
항상 파스타를 만들어요."
See, Cheryl explained that for many of her kids,
쉐릴이 말하길 많은 학생들이
there were no meals on the weekends.
주말에 밥을 못먹는다고 합니다.
No meals on Saturday.
토요일에도 굶고
No meals on Sunday, either.
일요일에도 굶고요.
So she cooked pasta because she wanted to make sure
그래서 파스타를 요리한다고 합니다.
she cooked something she knew her children would eat.
학생들이 제대로 한끼를 먹었으면 하는 마음에서
Something that would stick to their ribs, she said.
파스타가 아이들에게 피가 되고 살이 되고
Something that would fill them up.
그래서 아이들이 배부르도록 말이죠.
Cheryl talked about how, by the time Monday came,
쉐릴씨는 월요일이 되면
her kids' hunger pangs were so intense
아이들은 너무 배고파서
that they couldn't even begin to think about learning.
공부할 생각조차 못한다고 하더군요..
Food was the only thing on their mind.
아이들 머릿속에는
The only thing.
온통 먹을 것 생각 뿐이랍니다.
And unfortunately, the stats -- they tell the same story.
그리고 불행히도 관련 통계치도 이를 증명해줍니다
So, let's put this into the context of a child.
한 아이에게 이 이야기를 대입해봅시다.
And we're going to focus on
하루에서 가장 중요한 식사인
the most important meal of the day, breakfast.
아침 식사에 초점을 맞춰서 말입니다.
Meet Allison.
여기 앨리슨이라는 소녀가 있습니다.
She's 12 years old,
12살이고
she's smart as a whip
정말 똑똑합니다.
and she wants to be a physicist when she grows up.
장래희망은 물리학자입니다.
If Allison goes to a school that serves a nutritious breakfast
앨리슨이 학교에서
to all of their kids,
영양이 풍부한 아침을 먹을 수 있다면
here's what's going to follow.
다음과 같은 일이 벌어지게 됩니다.
Her chances of getting a nutritious meal,
과일과 우유, 또는 저당 저염의
one with fruit and milk, one lower in sugar and salt,
영양가를 섭취할 확률이
dramatically increase.
수직상승하게 됩니다.
Allison will have a lower rate of obesity than the average kid.
그럼 평균보다 낮은 비만율이 낮아질 겁니다.
She'll have to visit the nurse less.
병원에 갈 필요도 없고
She'll have lower levels of anxiety and depression.
분노나 우울 또한 줄어들 것이고
She'll have better behavior.
행동도 착해지고
She'll have better attendance, and she'll show up on time more often.
출석률도 높아지고 지각하는 일도 없겠죠.
Why?
왜일까요?
Well, because there's a good meal waiting for her at school.
학교에서 양질의 식사를 제공하기 때문입니다.
Overall, Allison is in much better health
종합적으로 앨리슨은
than the average school kid.
보통 아이들보다 훨씬 건강해지는 거죠.
So what about that kid
그렇다면 아침식사가 없는 학교를 다니는
who doesn't have a nutritious breakfast waiting for him?
아이의 경우는 어떨까요?
Well, meet Tommy.
여기 토미라는 남학생이 있습니다.
He's also 12. He's a wonderful kid.
역시 12살이고 착한 아이예요.
He wants to be a doctor.
장래희망은 의사입니다.
By the time Tommy is in kindergarten,
유치원에 다닐 때부터
he's already underperforming in math.
수학을 잘 하지 못했습니다.
By the time he's in third grade,
3학년이 되었을 때
he's got lower math and reading scores.
수학 및 읽기 수업에서 낮은 점수를 받습니다.
By the time he's 11,
11살이 되었을 때에도
it's more likely that Tommy will have to have repeated a grade.
똑같은 점수를 받게 될 겁니다.
Research shows that kids who do not have consistent nourishment,
연구에 따르면 꾸준히 영양분을 섭취하지 못하면
particularly at breakfast,
특히, 아침식사에서
have poor cognitive function overall.
인지기능이 전반적으로 떨어지게 됩니다.
So how widespread is this problem?
그렇다면 이런 문제가 얼마나 퍼져있을까요?
Well, unfortunately, it's pervasive.
불행히도 전국 각지에 퍼져있어요.
Let me give you two stats
두 가지만 말씀드릴게요.
that seem like they're on opposite ends of the issue,
서로 반대되는 이야기지만
but are actually two sides of the same coin.
동전의 양면처럼 동시에 일어나는 일입니다.
On the one hand,
한쪽 면은
one in six Americans are food insecure,
미국인 6명 중 1명은 식사를 제대로 못한다는 겁니다.
including 16 million children -- almost 20 percent --
아이 1600만 명을 포함한 대략 20%는
are food insecure.
한 끼도 먹기 힘듭니다.
In this city alone, in New York City,
뉴욕시만 하더라도
474,000 kids under the age of 18 face hunger every year.
매년 18세 이하 아이들 중 약 47만명이 굶주림과 싸웁니다
It's crazy.
말도 안 되는 일이죠.
On the other hand,
그런데
diet and nutrition is the number one cause of preventable death and disease
사망과 질병을 막는 최고의 방법이
in this country, by far.
"잘 먹기"라는 겁니다.
And fully a third of the kids that we've been talking about tonight
방금 이야기한 아이들의 3분의 1은
are on track to have diabetes in their lifetime.
살면서 당뇨병에 걸립니다.
Now, what's hard to put together but is true
얼마나 많은지 알수 없지만 확실한 것은
is that, many times, these are the same children.
아이들은 모두 똑같아요.
So they fill up on the unhealthy and cheap calories
주변에서 흔히 구할수 있는
that surround them in their communities and that their families can afford.
불량식품 등으로 자주 배를 채웁니다.
But then by the end of the month,
하지만 월말이 되면
food stamps run out or hours get cut at work,
식품구입권이 바닥나거나 근무 시간이 깎여서
and they don't have the money to cover the basic cost of food.
돈이 없어 기본적인 식사도 못해요.
But we should be able to solve this problem, right?
이 문제를 해결야합니다.
We know what the answers are.
우린 그 해결책을 알고 있어요.
As part of my work at the White House, we instituted a program
저는 백악관에 근무할 때
that for all schools that had 40 percent more low-income kids,
저소득층 가정 학생이 40%가 넘는 학교에
we could serve breakfast and lunch to every kid in that school.
아침, 점심을 제공하는 프로그램을 도입했습니다.
For free.
무료로 말이죠.
This program has been incredibly successful,
아이들에게 영양가있는 아침을 제공하는 과정에서
because it helped us overcome a very difficult barrier
어려운 장애를 극복하는 걸 도왔다는 점에서
when it came to getting kids a nutritious breakfast.
프로그램은 성공적이었어요.
And that was the barrier of stigma.
그 장애는 바로 "창피함"입니다.
See, schools serve breakfast before school,
원래 학교에서 제공하는 아침은
and it was only available for the poor kids.
가난한 학생만 이용할 수 있었죠.
So everybody knew who was poor and who needed government help.
당연히 누가 가난한 집 아이인지 모두 알게되죠.
Now, all kids, no matter how much or how little their parents make,
하지만 이제는 부모소득이 어떻건 간에
have a lot of pride.
아이들은 모두 자신있게 행동할 수 있죠.
So what happened?
어떤 효과가 있었을까요?
Well, the schools that have implemented this program
이 프로그램을 시행한 학교에서
saw an increase in math and reading scores by 17.5 percent.
수학과 읽기 부분에 점수가 약 17.5%가 상승했어요.
17.5 percent.
17.5%요.
And research shows that when kids have a consistent, nutritious breakfast,
꾸준히 아침을 든든히 먹으면
their chances of graduating increase by 20 percent.
졸업할 확률도 20%까지 증가한다는 연구도 있습니다.
20 percent.
자그마치 20%요.
When we give our kids the nourishment they need,
아이들에게 필요한 영양분을 주는 것은
we give them the chance to thrive,
아이들에게 성공할 기회를 주는 거예요.
both in the classroom and beyond.
학교에 있을 때도 졸업한 후에도 말입니다.
Now, you don't have to trust me on this,
저를 못믿으실지도 모르니
but you should talk to Donna Martin.
도나 마틴의 이야길 들어보죠.
I love Donna Martin.
전 도나 마틴을 정말 좋아합니다.
Donna Martin is the school nutrition director at Burke County
도나는 조지아 주 웨인즈브로 버크카운티에 있는 학교에서
in Waynesboro, Georgia.
수석 영양사입니다.
Burke County is one of the poorest districts
버크카운티는 미국에서
in the fifth-poorest state in the country,
가장 가난한 5개 주(州) 중 하나입니다.
and about 100 percent of Donna's students live at or below the poverty line.
그리고 도나의 학생들 대부분 빈곤선에 못미치는 생활수준입니다.
A few years ago,
몇 년 전
Donna decided to get out ahead of the new standards that were coming,
도나는 먼저 영양기준을 개선하기로 했어요.
and overhaul her nutrition standards.
영양기준을 면밀히 점검해서
She improved and added fruit and vegetables and whole grains.
식단에 과일, 채소와 통밀을 추가해서
She served breakfast in the classroom to all of her kids.
아이들 모두 아침을 먹게했습니다.
And she implemented a dinner program.
그리고 디너프로그램도 시행했어요.
Why?
왜냐면
Well, many of her kids didn't have dinner when they went home.
아이들이 집에선 저녁을 굶기 때문이에요.
So how did they respond?
아이들은 반응이 어땠을까요.
Well, the kids loved the food.
정말 좋아했죠.
They loved the better nutrition,
영양분이 가득한 음식을 먹으니
and they loved not being hungry.
배고픔을 느끼지 않아서 좋아했죠.
But Donna's biggest supporter came from an unexpected place.
그런데 의외의 후원자가 등장했어요.
His name from Eric Parker,
에릭 파커라는 남자는
and he was the head football coach for the Burke County Bears.
버크 카운티 베어스 풋봄팀 수석 코치입니다.
Now, Coach Parker had coached mediocre teams for years.
팀 성적도 변변치 못했습니다.
The Bears often ended in the middle of the pack --
대회에서도 대부분 중위권을 넘어서지 못했죠.
a big disappointment in one of the most passionate football states
풋볼에 대한 기대치도 높은 지역이라 그런지
in the Union.
당연히 실망도 컸죠.
But the year Donna changed the menus,
그런데 그 해, 도나가 식단를 바꾸자
the Bears not only won their division,
베어스는 리그뿐만 아니라
they went on to win the state championship,
주(州) 선수권대회에서도 우승을 차지합니다.
beating the Peach County Trojans
피치카운티 트로이를
28-14.
28 대 14로 꺾고 말입니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
And Coach Parker,
그리고 파커 코치는
he credited that championship to Donna Martin.
모두 도나 덕분이라고 했죠.
When we give our kids the basic nourishment,
아이들이 기본적인 영양섭취만 잘하게끔 해줘도
they're going to thrive.
아이들은 알아서 성공합니다.
And it's not just up to the Cheryl Barbaras
전 세계에서 쉘리 바바라와
and the Donna Martins of the world.
도나 마틴만이 할 수 있는 일이 아닙니다.
It's on all of us.
모두가 해야 할 일입니다.
And feeding our kids the basic nutrition is just the starting point.
가장 먼저 할 일은 아이들에게 기본적인 영양분을 주는 겁니다.
What I've laid out is really a model
제가 지금껏 당면한 수많은 문제들을 대부분
for so many of the most pressing issues that we face.
해결하기 위한 모델을 구축해왔지만
If we focus on the simple goal of properly nourishing ourselves,
영양분만 적절하게 섭취하자는 간단한 목표에만 초점을 맞춰도
we could see a world that is more stable and secure;
전세계가 더 안정되고 안전해질 겁니다.
we could dramatically improve our economic productivity;
경제적 생산성도 대단히 개선할 수 있고
we could transform our health care
의료분야도 변할 것입니다
and we could go a long way
그리고 장기적으로
in ensuring that the Earth can provide for generations to come.
다음 세대에 더 건강한 세상을 물려줄 수 있습니다.
Food is that place where our collective efforts
우리 모두 노력한다면
can have the greatest impact.
식량문제를 크게 변화시킬 수 있습니다.
So we have to ask ourselves: What is the right question?
그러니 스스로 질문을 해야합니다 올바른 질문이 무엇일까?
What would happen
꾸준히 더 영양가 좋은 음식을 먹으면
What would be the impact?
어떤 영향을 끼칠까?
Cheryl Barbara,
쉘리 바바라
Donna Martin,
도나 마틴
Coach Parker and the Burke County Bears --
파커 코치 그리고 버크 카운티 베어스는
I think they know the answer.
그 해답을 알 것 같네요.
Thank you guys so very much.
들어주셔서 정말 감사합니다.
(Applause)
(박수)